Hello, I am going to present very briefly
how the algorithm random forest works
Well, we start with a rationale of the term
and we say that the combination of learning
models
increases the classification accuracy
When we use different learning models we can
increase the accuracy of classification, which
is the main idea of a technique that is called
bagging
And bagging, the main idea is to average noisy
and unbiased models in order to create another
model with a lower variance, in terms of classification
Now, we describe the random forest, a very
brief definition
Random forest algorithm works as a large collection
of the correlated decision trees
Well, the name forest is because we use a
lot of decision trees
But this algorithm of random forest creates
a lot of decision trees and use them to make
a classification
That is why it is a technique based on the
bagging technique, that we presented before
So, how the random forest algorithm works?
Lets see
We show here in this example a matrix S
Suppose this matrix S is a matrix of training
samples that we will submit to the algorithm
to create a classification model
In this case f A 1, f B 1, f C 1, these are
a lot of features, for example the f A 1 is
the feature A of the first sample
And we continue in all the samples up to N
So, the f B N is the feature B of the Nth
sample
And also we have in the last column here the
C 1 and C N, which means that we have lots
of features and we have a training class
So the aim is to create a random forest to
classify this sample set
How the algorithm works, in detail?
Well, we get this sample set and from this
sample set we create a lot of subsets with
random values
Which means that, for example, in the first
subset we used the line number 12, the line
number 15 and also the line number 35
And also some other random elements here
So we get a subset from that previously shown
sample set and from this element we create
a decision tree number 1
Then we make another random subset with different
values, we can see that we have the sample
number 2, sample number 6 and the sample number
20 and many others
With these values we can create a decision
tree number 2
And from this M sample we can create the decision
tree number M
So, this is why we call it a forest
Because we have a lot of decision trees
And after we created all of these decision
trees
I am going to repeat that used different samples
from each of the sample set here, we created
a subset with random samples
Then with all these decision trees we have
different variations of the main classification
Then we are going to use all of this decision
trees to create a ranking of classifiers
So, in the next example here we show how we
can make the class prediction
I showed 4 examples of decision trees here
only to see how the class prediction will
work
In this case we have 4 decision trees, our
forest is composed by 4 trees
If we have a new element to classify we are
going to ask for the first tree what is the
prediction
Suppose the first tree said that the classification
of this sample is class 1, and then we called
to the second decision tree and it says that
is class number 3 and then the other says
that it is class number 1 and the other says
is class number 2
So we have 4 decision trees, independent decision
trees here which were created using subsamples
of the entire sample set
And now we can account for the number of votes
for each class
It is obvious that we have 1 vote here and
another vote here for class 1, so we have
2 votes for class 1 and a single vote for
class 2 and a single vote for class 3
So the result is going to be class 1
This random forest classified all the elements
and the class 1 was the selected class of
this classification
So it is a very simple process, the difficult
here is to create a lot of decision trees
but the creation of decision tree belongs
to the algorithm of decision trees
So, this is the idea behind the random forest
algorithm
Here I provide some references
The main reference is this one, Random Forests,
which was published in 2001
And also I used this book to create this presentation
So this is how Random Forest algorithm works